Andrew Dasburg Papers
Andrew Dasburg Papers
1908-1981
Dasburg, Andrew, 1887-1979.
3.8 linear ft.
Papers of the American painter. Correspondence, photographs of work, exhibition catalogs, and miscellaneous published material. Correspondents include William C. Agee, John H. Bradley, Alexander Brook, Louise Bryant, Jerry Bywaters, Witter Bynner, Peggy Church, Howard Cook, Philip Dedrick, Arthur Davison Ficke, Edwin Gamble, Marsden Hartley, Richard Hollander, Lila Howard, D.H. Lawrence, Ward Lockwood, Erle Loran, Mabel Dodge Luhan, Henry Lee McFee, John Marin, Georgia O'Keeffe, Louis Ribak, Morgan Russell, Lesley Simpson, Carl Van Vechten, Victor White, Owen Wister, and others.
148927
Biographical History
Andrew Michael Dasburg (1887-1979) was an American modernist painter and teacher. Born in Paris, he attended the Art Students League of New York and became a leading early cubist.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Andrew Dasburg Papers contain subject files, correspondence, writings, and memorabilia.
Subject files contains a detailed speech about Dasburg's early life, documenting his place of birth, his childhood and education, and the development of his talents. An interview with Dasburg in 1964 includes his thoughts about his work and that of other contemporary painters, and a discussion about Mabel Dodge Luhan. Also in this section is a list of painting prices handwritten by Dasburg, in which various types of paintings are listed with their selling price. Also included are photographs of some of Dasburg's work, both titled and untitled.
Correspondence covers the years from 1908 to 1971, and includes letters from family members and relatives (Alfred Dasburg, Daphne Dasburg, Andrew Kerr, Deborah Park, Diana Schwalbe, Owen Wister). There are many letters from patrons and art collectors, foremost among them Edwin Gamble and Mabel Dodge Luhan. Museums and art galleries that have shown his work and have corresponded with Dasburg include the Denver Art Museum, Frank K. M. Rehn, Inc., Kennedy Galleries, Inc., Leone Kahl Gallery, and the Museum of New Mexico.
Dasburg corresponded with many contemporary artists of his time including Kenneth Adams, Ernest Blumenschein, Alexander Brook, Paul Burlin, Lez Haas, Marsden Hartley, Arthur Lee, Ward Lockwood, Henry Lee McFee, John Marin, Judson Smith, and Robert Walker. Other prominent individuals connected to the art world with whom he corresponded include William C. Agee, Louise Bryant, Jerry Bywaters, F. Van Deren Coke, Lyon Hayes, and Georgia O'Keeffe.
Writings contains Dasburg's lecture notes about painting and his lectures as transcribed by an unidentified student. These notes reveal how Dasburg thought about painting, what he considered important in art, and his thoughts about how a painter relates to what he sees and what he puts on canvas. There are several articles written by Dasburg between 1932 and 1951; the topics include Cubism, and his position on exhibition rental policy.
Also in this collection are catalogs from Exhibitions of Dasburg's one-man shows as well as shows in which he had only one or two works. Dating from the 1930s to the 1970s, these catalogs feature Dasburg together with many of the artists with whom he corresponded.
Printed material about Dasburg contains articles and clippings dated from 1949 to 1981. They concern his exhibitions, his honors and awards, and his death in 1979.
Memorabilia contains printed material consisting of articles and clippings about Dasburg's correspondents. There are also articles about the pai nter Dasburg discovered, John Kane. Also under Memorabilia are the published works of Milton Brown, The Story of the Armory Show; Ward Lockwood, The Marin I knew: A Personal Reminiscence; and Gertrude Stein, Portrait of Mabel Dodge at Villa Curonia. Also included are individual issues of The Arts, Hue and Cry, and Laughing Horse.
Miscellany contains a personal note written an the back of an envelope, an address, and an unused tax form.
Arrangement of the Collection
Each series is arranged alphabetically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Agee, William C.; Bradley, John Hodgdon, 1898-; Brook, Alexander, 1898-1980.; Bryant, Louise, 1885-1936.; Bywaters, Jerry.; Bynner, Witter, 1881-1968.; Church, Peggy Pond, 1903-1986.; Cook, Howard Norton, 1901-1980.; Dasburg, Andrew, 1887-1979.; Dedrick, Philip.; Ficke, Arthur Davison, 1883-1945.; Gamble, Edwin.; Hartley, Marsden, 1877-1943.; Hollander, Richard.; Howard, Lila.; Lawrence, D. H. (David Herbert), 1885-1930.; Lockwood, Ward.; Loran, Erle, 1905-1999.; Luhan, Mabel Dodge, 1879-1962.; McFee, Henry Lee, 1886-1953.; Marin, John, 1870-1953.; O'Keeffe, Georgia, 1997-1986.; Ribak, Louis, 1902-1979.; Russell, Morgan, 1886-1953.; Simpson, Lesley Byrd, 1891-1984.; Van Vechten, Carl, 1880-1964.; White, Victor, 1902-1960.; Wister, Owen, 1860-1938.; Art, American.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Artist colonies -- New Mexico -- Taos.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Painting, American -- Southwestern States.; Cubism -- United States.; Correspondence.; Exhibition catalogs.; Photographs.; Artists.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Subject files
  - "Andrew Dasburg - Artist and Influence of the 1920s" - speech, undated (Box 1)
  - Interview with Dasburg, July 2, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Painting prices, undated (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - of Dasburg, undated (Box 1)
    - of a) Dasburg Castle, b) Blacksmith at Nittel, Germany (Box 1)
    - "Aspens" (Box 1)
    - "Clouds", 1930 (Box 1)
    - "Coffee Plantation" (Box 1)
    - "Cottonwoods", 1940 (Box 1)
    - "Fruit Still Life", 1931 (Box 1)
    - "Fruit Still Life", 1949 (Box 1)
    - "Garlic Bulbs" (Box 1)
    - "Hondo Canyon", 1930 (Box 1)
    - "Joseph Bakos", 1923 (Box 1)
    - "Lamy Road", 1930 (Box 1)
    - "Landscape", 1932 (Box 1)
    - "Llano Quemado", 1950 (Box 1)
    - "Orchard" I, 1950 (Box 1)
    - "Orchard" II, 1950 (Box 1)
    - "Orchard In a Windstorm" III, 1950 (Box 1)
    - "Picuris Mt." (Box 1)
    - "Pines" (Box 1)
    - "Ranchos de Taos", 1935 (Box 1)
    - "Sangrede Cristo Mountains" (Box 1)
    - "Sepia Ink Landscape" (Box 1)
    - "Still Life with Mandolin" (Box 1)
    - "Tree", 1949 (Box 1)
    - Flower still lifes - untitled (Box 1)
    - Portraits - untitled (Box 1)
    - Sketches of nude models - untitled (Box 1)
    - Vegetable still lifes - untitled (Box 1)
    - Village buildings - untitled (Box 1)
    - of Dasburg's work - duplicates (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Adams, Kenneth M. (and Helen), 1923; 1930,; 1957-1959,; 1970 (Box 1)
  - Adkins, Eugene B., 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Agee, William C., 1964-1966 (Box 1)
  - Alexandre Rabow Galleries, 1955 (Box 1)
  - American Art Research Council, 1943 (Box 1)
  - American Federation of Arts, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Archives of American Art, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Austin, Mary (about Diego Rivera), 1933 (Box 1)
  - Bailey, Susa C., 1960-1961 (Box 1)
  - Baker, Marilyn, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Baldinger, Wallace Spencer, 1937 (Box 1)
  - Bewley, Edwin E., 1956 (Box 1)
  - Bibbons, Julia, 1970; undated (Box 1)
  - Blanc, W. P., 1956-1957 (Box 1)
  - Blumberg, Morrie, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Blumenschein, Ernest, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Bradley, John Hodgdon, 1933; 1956-1957,; 1959 (Box 1)
  - Brill, A. A., 1928 (Box 1)
  - Brook, Alexander, 1924; 1965,; 1971,; undated (Box 1)
  - Brown, Dorothy H., 1959 (Box 1)
  - Browne, Diana A., 1971 (Box 1)
  - Bryant, Louise, 1920 (Box 1)
  - Burlin, Paul, 1924 (Box 1)
  - Bynner, Witter, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Bywaters, Jerry, 1956-1957; 1959,; 1960 (Box 1)
  - Church, Peggy Pond, 1955; 1957,; 1960,; 1963 (Box 1)
  - Clemmens, Lucienne Chinard, 1970; undated (Box 1)
  - Coke, F. Van Deren, 1959; 1964,; 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - Colorado Springs Fine Arts Center, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Cook, Howard, 1966-1967; 1969-1971 (Box 1)
  - Cottam, Betty, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Cramer, Florence B., 1955 (Box 1)
  - Dasburg, Alfred V. (and Ann), 1955-1959; 1961,; 1966,; 1968-1971,; undated (Box 1)
  - Dasburg, Daphne, 1955; 1965,; 1968 (Box 1)
  - Dedrick, Philip, 1953-1959; 1965-1967 (Box 1)
  - Denver Art Museum, 1971 (Box 1)
  - de Schulthess, Amalia Mimi, 1955-1961; 1963,; 1970 (Box 2)
  - Dozier, Otis, 1957 (Box 2)
  - Dundee Designs, 1955 (Box 2)
  - Elkort, Martin, 1959; undated (Box 2)
  - Ellis, Robert C. (and Rosa and Eri), 1963; 1965,; 1968,; 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Endowment of 1967, 1967-1968; 1970 (Box 2)
  - Erickson, R. J. "Eric", 1929-1930; undated (Box 2)
  - Erwin, Dorothy, 1958; 1965,; 1969,; 1971,; undated (Box 2)
  - Feeley, Gladys, 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Ficke, Arthur (and Gladys), 1928-1929; 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Fifth Avenue Gallery, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Fisher, Alan, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Ford Foundation, 1958-1960; 1962 (Box 2)
  - Frank K. M. Rehn, Inc., 1935 (Box 2)
  - Gamble, Edwin, 1950-1971; undated; 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Garber, Benjamin, 1963-1965; undated (Box 2)
  - Garrison, Lewis V., 1957 (Box 2)
  - Gillespie, Sallie, 1965; 1968,; undated (Box 2)
  - Goodwin, Mary, 1967; 1969,; undated (Box 2)
  - Graham, Donald S., 1971 (Box 2)
  - Griffin, John H. "Howard", 1957; 1959 (Box 2)
  - Haas, Lez (and Eleanor), 1955; 1958,; 1963-1964,; 1970 (Box 2)
  - Hagerman, Herbert J., 1933 (Box 2)
  - Harper, Pauline, 1957; 1959,; undated (Box 2)
  - Hartley, Marsden, undated (Box 2)
  - Hendrickson, Albert Nels, 1959 (Box 2)
  - Hollander, Richard, 1955; 1959,; 1965-1966,; 1971 (Box 2)
  - Howard, Lila, 1957-1960; 1964-1966 (Box 2)
  - Hutchinson, W. H., 1970 (Box 2)
  - John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation, 1932 (Box 2)
  - Jonson Gallery, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Kackley, Fritz, 1968-1969; 1971 (Box 2)
  - Kassler, Charles Jr., 1967 (Box 2)
  - Kennedy Galleries, Inc., 1971 (Box 3)
  - Kerr, Andrew III, 1968 (Box 3)
  - King, David W., 1966 (Box 3)
  - Kool, Alice Acker, 1959-1960; 1962 (Box 3)
  - Lawrence, D. H., 1924; undated (Box 3)
  - Lee, Arthur, 1927 (Box 3)
  - Leone Kahl Gallery, 1965 (Box 3)
  - Linden, Carl Eric, 1933 (Box 3)
  - Lockwood, Ward, 1955; 1957,; 1960 (Box 3)
  - Loran, Erle, 1957; 1959,; 1970-1971 (Box 3)
  - Luhan, Mabel Dodge, 1955; 1957-1959,; undated (Box 3)
  - Lyon, Hayes, 1955; 1957,; 1959,; 1968-1971 (Box 3)
  - McFee, Henry Lee, 1930-1931 (Box 3)
  - Marin, John (and Norma), 1929-1931; 1970,; undated (Box 3)
  - Montgomery, Arthur, 1955; 1957 (Box 3)
  - Mozley, Loren, 1957; 1959,; 1969-1971 (Box 3)
  - Munson-Williams-Proctor Institute, 1957; 1962 (Box 3)
  - Museum of New Mexico, 1955; 1959,; 1970 (Box 3)
  - Nash, Willard, undated (Box 3)
  - Nehls, Edward, 1956 (Box 3)
  - O'Keeffe, Georgia, 1931 (Box 3)
  - O'Rourke, Laurence J., 1970 (Box 3)
  - Park, Deborah, 1955; 1966-1967,; undated (Box 3)
  - Phillips, Burton, 1961; 1963,; 1965,; 1968,; undated (Box 3)
  - Phillips, Sandra S., 1970 (Box 3)
  - Pitkin, Charles D., 1970 (Box 3)
  - Reeder, Dickson (and Flora), 1957; undated (Box 3)
  - Reichman, Fred, 1955; 1957 (Box 3)
  - Ribak, Louis, 1956; 1967-1969 (Box 3)
  - Rogoway, Alfred (and Marjorie), 1955-1956; 1958-1960,; 1965-1966,; 1968,; undated (Box 3)
  - Ronnebeck, Arnold, 1930; undated (Box 3)
  - Rosenstone, Robert A., 1970 (Box 3)
  - Russell, Morgan, 1908; 1910-1915 (Box 3)
  - Saebean, Samuel, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Sanger, Margery, 1957; 1971 (Box 3)
  - Schack, William, 1957 (Box 3)
  - Schwab, Arnold T., 1971 (Box 3)
  - Schwalbe, Diana, 1955; 1959,; 1961,; 1965-1968,; undated (Box 3)
  - Shiras, Mary, 1955 (Box 3)
  - Simpson, Lesley (and Marian), 1932-1933 (Box 3)
  - Smith, Anita M., 1957 (Box 3)
  - Smith, Emily Guthrie, 1958-1959 (Box 3)
  - Smith, Judson, 1928; 1932,; 1955,; 1959-1960 (Box 3)
  - State of New Mexico, 1932; 1979 (Box 3)
  - Stevenson, J. H. "Joe", 1933 (Box 3)
  - Striebel, John, 1956 (Box 3)
  - Stroh, Earl, 1955-1958 (Box 3)
  - Swaine, Ruth, 1956; 1958,; 1960-1961,; undated (Box 3)
  - Tears, Ruth, undated (Box 3)
  - Todd, Robertson, Todd Engineering Corporation (about Diego Rivera), 1933 (Box 3)
  - Trentham, Eugene "Steve", 1957 (Box 3)
  - University of Kansas Museum of Art, 1970 (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan Museum of Art, 1953 (Box 3)
  - University of Nebraska Art Galleries, 1957 (Box 3)
  - University of New Mexico, 1958 (Box 3)
  - University of New Mexico, College of Fine Arts, 1965 (Box 3)
  - Van Vechten, Carl, 1922; 1925,; 1928,; 1930,; undated (Box 3)
  - Van Wagner, Judy, 1969 (Box 4)
  - Walker, Robert, 1925; 1928-1931,; undated (Box 4)
  - Walker, Robert (and Mariella), 1971 (Box 4)
  - Waters, Frank, undated (Box 4)
  - Wells, Mason B., 1957 (Box 4)
  - Weronke, Ann, 1968-1969 (Box 4)
  - Weronke, Murilla, 1968-1969 (Box 4)
  - White, Victor, 1955; 1957-1959,; 1964-1966,; 1969,; undated (Box 4)
  - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1936 (Box 4)
  - Williams, Elizabeth, 1952 (Box 4)
  - Wister, Frances Mitchell, undated (Box 4)
  - Wister, Owen J., 1955; 1959-1960,; 1965,; undated (Box 4)
  - Wolman, Cecil, 1930; 1957,; 1960-1961,; 1964-1967,; 1970-1971,; undated (Box 4)
  - Wood, Bernadine, 1968-1969 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1931; 1955-1960,; 1964-1965,; 1967-1971,; undated (Box 4)
- Writings
  - Lecture notes on painting, 1949-1950 (Box 5)
  - Lecture notes as transcribed by a student, 1950 (Box 5)
  - Articles by Dasburg, 1923; 1936,; 1951 (Box 5)
- Exhibitions
  - Catalogs
    - Art Students League of New York, 1951 (Box 5)
    - A Selection of Works From the Art Galleries at the University of Nebraska, 1963 (Box 5)
    - The Drawings of Andrew Dasburg, 1966 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous, 1936; 1939,; 1940,; 1957,; 1960,; 1966,; 1970 (Box 5)
  - Mailings, 1966 (Box 5)
  - Photographs of Dasburg's work in unidentified gallery, undated (Box 5)
- Printed material about
  - Articles, 1959; 1966,; 1981,; undated (Box 5)
  - Clippings, 1949; 1951,; 1960,; 1966-1967,; 1979,; undated (Box 5)
- Memorabilia
  - Printed material
    - Articles (miscellaneous), undated (Box 5)
    - Articles - John Kane, 1937; undated (Box 5)
    - Articles - "Santa Fe - Its Years of Art", Nov. 12, 1967 (Box 5)
    - Clippings (miscellaneous), 1946; 1958,; 1971,; undated (Box 5)
    - Clippings - "El Crepusculo", Oct. 15, 1953 (Box 5)
  - Published material
    - Brown, Milton W., The Story of the Armory Show, 1963 (Box 6)
    - Hunter, Sam, Modern American Painting and Sculpture, 1959 (Box 6)
    - Lockwood, Ward, The Marin I Knew: A Personal Reminiscence, undated (Box 6)
    - Stein, Gertrude, Portrait of Mabel Dodge at the Villa Curonia, 1913 (Box 6)
    - The University of New Mexico Bulletin, Aug. 14, 1953 (Box 6)
    - The Arts, July 1924; Nov. 1926 (Box 6)
    - The Hue and Cry, 1926 (Box 6)
    - Laughing Horse, Summer 1929 (Box 6)
- Miscellaneous
  - Miscellanea, personal note written an the outside of an envelope, an address, and an unused income tax form (Box 6)